Finding Aid for the Helen H. Lyman Papers, circa 1890-2002 (bulk 1955-1998)
State University of New York at Buffalo. University Archives
- Professional, II.
  - U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare, Office of Education, Office of Libraries and Learning Technologies, II.E
    - Project L0029JA, "The Blue Collar Adult's Information Needs, Seeking Behavior and Use," by Thomas Childers and Joyce Post, Mar. 1976 (Box-folder 17.7-17.8)
    - Project 475AH60019 "The Latino Communications Project," by Daniel F. Duran, Margaret E. Monroe, Oct. 1977 (Box-folder 34.6)
    - "Patterns in Reading and Information-Seeking Activities": abstract, project co-directed with James Krikelas, 1978 (Box-folder 17.9)
    - CRC Education and Human Development, Inc. "Libraries in Literacy," by Ester Gottlieb Smith, 1981; includes correspondence, final report draft, notes, interview schedules and final report.[5 folders] (Box-folder 17.10-18.2)
    - U.S. Committee on Education and Labor, "Statement of Helen Huguenor Lyman before the House Postsecondary Education Subcommittee on Reauthorization of the Library Services and Construction Act (LSCA)," March, 1983; includes notes. (Box-folder 18.3)
    - U.S. Department of Education, Library Literacy Program, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 18.4)
- Teachings, III.
  - Correspondence, 1967-1986, 1992, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 19.1-19.2)
  - "Adult Education": notes and research materials used in courses, 1941, 1976, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 19.3)
  - University of Wisconsin-Madison, 1966-1977, III.A
    - L.S. 503, "Introduction to Library Collection Building," 1974, undated (Box-folder 19.4-19.5)
    - L.S. 503, "Introduction to Library Collection Building": handouts, 1974-1976, undated; includes syllabus, assignments, readings, bibliographies. (Box-folder 19.6)
    - L.S. 503, "Introduction to Library Collection Building": general lecture notes, research, 1974, undated (Box-folder 19.7-19.8)
    - L.S. 503, "Introduction to Library Collection Building": topical lecture notes, research, 1974, undated; includes introduction, budget, book reviewing, definitions. (Box-folder 19.9-19.10)
    - L.S. 503, "Introduction to Library Collection Building": lecture notes, research - acquisition policies, 1961, 1973, undated (Box-folder 19.11)
    - L.S. 503, "Introduction to Library Collection Building": lecture notes, research - bibliographies, 1959, 1967, 1973, undated (Box-folder 19.12)
    - L.S. 503, "Introduction to Library Collection Building": lecture notes, research - book selection, 1975, undated (Box-folder 19.13)
    - L.S. 503, "Introduction to Library Collection Building": lecture notes, research - censorship, 1960-1976, undated; includes case studies, speeches, pamphlets, lists, ALA Library Bill of Rights, clippings, reprints, Freedom and Communication by Dan Lacy, 1965. (Box-folder 20.1-20.4)
    - L.S. 503, "Introduction to Library Collection Building": lecture notes, research - evaluation, 1972, undated; includes Starting Out Right: Choosing books about black people for your children, by the Wisconsin Department of Public Instruction, 1972. (Box-folder 20.5)
    - L.S. 503, "Introduction to Library Collection Building": lecture notes, research - magazines and serials, 1974, undated (Box-folder 20.6)
    - L.S. 503, "Introduction to Library Collection Building": lecture notes, research - general publishing, 1970-1973, undated; includes remainders, minority publishers, wholesalers. (Box-folder 20.7-20.8)
    - L.S. 503, "Introduction to Library Collection Building": lecture notes, research - alternative presses, 1972, undated; includes Chips Directory of high school and junior high school underground papers, 1972, Free Ranger Advertising Coop. Directory, undated (Box-folder 20.9)
    - L.S. 503, "Introduction to Library Collection Building": lecture notes, research - publishing, out-of-print books, circa 1972, undated (Box-folder 20.10)
    - L.S. 530, "Adult Books," 1967 (Box-folder 21.1)
    - L.S. 841, "Reading Interests of Adults," 1967 (Box-folder 21.2)
    - L.S. 841, "Reading Interests of Adults," handouts, assignments, 1967-1977, undated; includes course schedules, bibliographies (Box-folder 21.3-21.5)
    - L.S. 841, "Reading Interests of Adults": "Book Talks & Book Reviewing," 1967 (Box-folder 21.6-21.7)
    - L.S. 841, "Reading Interests of Adults," lecture notes, research, 1961-1967, undated (Box-folder 21.8-21.11)
    - L.S. 841, "Reading Interests of Adults," 1972 (Box-folder 22.1-22.2)
    - L.S. 841, "Reading Interests of Adults," 1975 (disbound binder) (Box-folder 22.3-22.4)
    - L.S. 841, "Reading Interests of Adults," 1977 (disbound binder) (Box-folder 22.5-22.6)
    - L.S. 843, "Audio Visual Services in Libraries," 1971-1974, undated (Box-folder 22.7-22.8)
    - L.S. 843 (also L.S. 503) "Introduction to Library Collection Building," 1972-1974, 1985, undated (Box-folder 22.9-22.10)
  - University at Buffalo, 1977-1998, III.B
    - L.I.S. 551 "Adult Services," 1967 (Box-folder 22.11)
    - L.I.S 542 "Resources and Services for Adults," 1977-1997, undated; includes course readings, handouts, lectures, notes, essays, Elizabeth Burge. (Box-folder 22.12-24.5)
      (RESTRICTED: grievance removed to 35.5)
  - Student papers, III.C
    - Nancy J. Freeman, 1969, 1971 (Box-folder 24.6)
    - Laurence L. Sherril, 1972 (Box-folder 24.7-24.8)
    - Donna Curtis, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 24.9)
    - Sue Sherif, C. Horowitz 1975 (Box-folder 24.10)
    - Peter A. Neenan, 1977, 1986 (Box-folder 24.11-24.12)
    - Serafino Porcari, 1980 (Box-folder 24.13)
    - Others, 1981-1998 (Box-folder 24.14-24.15)
- Adult literacy resources, IV.
  - Articles, IV.A
    - Lloyd Vernor Ballard, The Public Library, 1937 (Box-folder 25.1)
    - Harbans S. Bhola, 1981, 1985, undated (Box-folder 25.2)
    - Elizabeth J. Burge, 1977, 1982-1999, undated; includes correspondence, "Developing Partnerships: A Report on Library-based Services for Distance Education Students in Northern Ontario," by E.J. Burge, J.E. Snow, J.L. Howard, undated (Box-folder 25.3-25.9)
    - K. Patricia Cross, 1978-1979; includes "Libraries in the Learning Society," typewritten speech, 1979. (Box-folder 25.10)
    - Nancy Harvey Davis and Pam Fitzgerald, "Literacy Clearinghouse," column in Library Journal, 1989-1992 (Box-folder 25.11)
    - Yekutiel Deligdisch, "The Reading Comprehension of Adult New Readers in Relation to Their Ethnic Backgrounds," under the supervision of Margaret E. Monroe, typewritten essay, 1971 (Box-folder 25.12-25.13)
    - Lois D. Flemming, "Community Education and Public Libraries: Cooperation or Conquest," typewritten essay, undated (Box-folder 25.14)
    - Judith D. Goyen, "Adult Illiteracy in Sydney," 1977 (Box-folder 26.1)
    - Suzanne Hildebrand, Cyril O. Houle, Roby Kidd, 1982, 1996, undated; includes obituary of Roby Kidd, 1982 (Box-folder 26.2)
    - Malcolm Knowles, Jorie Lester Mark, 1984 (Box-folder 26.3)
    - "The Library's Public: 1965," by members of L220, "The Public Library in the Political Process," Fall Semester, 1965-1966, School of Library & Information Services, University of Maryland: collection of typewritten essays. (Box-folder 26.4)
    - Angela Miles, "Confessions of a Harlequin Reader: Romance and the Fantasy of Male Mothering," typewritten essay, 1988 (Box-folder 26.5)
    - Helen Modra, 1976-1979, 1988; includes correspondence, vita. (Box-folder 26.6)
    - Margaret E. Monroe, 1971-1986, 1991, undated; includes "Partners for Lifelong Learning: Public Libraries and Adult Education," 1991. (Box-folder 26.7-26.10)
    - Rhea Joyce Rubin, 1975, 1981-1982, 1986 (Box-folder 26.11)
    - Joan P. Shevroy, "A Study of the Library Resource Use and Needs of Part-time Adult Returning Women at Jamestown Community College," (written for the School of Library and Information Studies at the University at Buffalo), 1984 (Box-folder 26.12)
    - John C. Shirk, "The Library Learning Climate Inventory: A Process for Understanding the Adult Learner," 1981 - Elizabeth Martinez Smith, "Chicanos and Libraries," typewritten essay, undated (Box-folder 26.13)
    - Unknown authors, typewritten essays, undated (Box-folder 26.14)
    - General articles, 1947, 1952-1999, 2002, undated; includes Ester Gottlieb Smith, 1984, Technology: The Surrender of Culture Technology by Neil Postman, 1992, executive summary from Adult Literacy in America by Irwin S. Kirsch et. al., 1993. (Box-folder 27.1-27.11)
    - Serials: issues on adult education/literacy, 1954-1994 (not inclusive); includes Bookmark, Wilson Library Bulletin, Wisconsin Library Bulletin. (Box-folder 30.7-30.9)
  - Handbooks and reports, IV.B
    - Ella Washington Griffin, Lets Help the Ten Million: Teaching Adults the Literacy Skills, 1960 (Box-folder 28.2)
    - Philip H. Ennis, Adult Book Reading in the United States, 1965; includes typed report, "An Exploratory Study on Illiteracy," 1969 (Box-folder 28.3)
    - E. Theodore Warren, "Seeds of Change," 1969 (Box-folder 28.4)
    - Patrick Penland, Advisory Counseling for Librarians, 1969 (Box-folder 28.5)
    - Free Library of Philadelphia, Reader Development Bibliography, 1974 (Box-folder 28.6)
    - National Assessment of Educational Progress, Reading Objectives, 1970, 1974 (Box-folder 28.7)
    - Genevieve M. Casey et. al., Public Library Service for the Urban Disadvantaged, 1972 (Box-folder 28.8)
    - The Office of Library Independent Study and Guidance Projects, College Entrance Examinations Board, The Role of Public Libraries in Supporting Adult Independent Learning: An Interim Assessment, 1974 (Box-folder 28.9)
    - National Advisory Council on Adult Education, A Target Population in Adult Education, 1974 (Box-folder 28.10)
    - The Office of Library Independent Study and Guidance Projects, College Entrance Examinations Board, A Guide to Understanding the Adult Learners, prepared by Ronald B. Szczypkowski, 1974 (Box-folder 29.1)
    - Edgar Dale and Joseph O'Rourke, The Living Word Vocabulary: the Words We Know: A National Vocabulary Inventory, 1976 (Box-folder 29.2)
    - Anabel P. Newman and Michael S. Parer, Lit-TV: Literary Instructor Training, a Five-Part TV/Film Workshop Handbook for Literacy Instructors, 1977 (Box-folder 29.3)
    - Jean E. Coleman, Literacy Training Project Report, 1978-1979; includes typewritten essay "The Social Responsibilities of Literacy Education in Public Libraries," undated (Box-folder 29.4)
    - Roger Lewis, Martin and Gill Pugmire, A Better Read, 1979 (Box-folder 29.5)
    - "Adult Literacy Resources," compiled by the Newcomer Services Branch of the Citizenship Division of the Ontario Ministry of Culture and Recreation, 1980 (Box-folder 29.6)
    - ALA, Libraries and Literacy: Closing the Education Gap, 1981 (Box-folder 29.7)
    - North York Public Library, Leading to Reading for Adults, vol. 2, 1981 (Box-folder 29.8)
    - Audrey A. Armstrong and Sally P. Hunt, Vital Guidelines: Tutor Training for an Adult Literacy Program, 1982 (Box-folder 29.9)
    - Martha A. Lane et. al., California Literacy Campaign Program Effectiveness Review, 1984 (Box-folder 30.1)
    - David Harman, Functional Illiteracy in the United States: Issues, Experiences, and Dilemmas, 1984 (Box-folder 30.2)
    - Debra Wilcox Johnson, Literacy and Libraries: A Planning Manual, 1985 (Box-folder 30.3)
    - Adult Literacy: A Policy Statement and Resource Guide for Cities, 1986 (Box-folder 30.4)
    - Altrusa International Foundation, 1986-1987; includes "Literacy Needs Assessment or LNA: A Tool for Assessing the Literacy Needs of a Local Community," edited by Carole S. Talan. (Box-folder 30.5)
    - The California State University (CSU)-The State University of New York (SUNY)-The City University of New York (CUNY) Joint Committee, 1996; includes A Framework for Quality: Information Resources and Library Services for Distance Learners, Ownership of New Works at the University: Unbundling of Rights and the Pursuit of Higher Learning. (Box-folder 30.6)
  - Literacy programs and projects, IV.C
    - Public library programs, 1966, 1972, 1976-1977, 1994, undated (Box-folder 31.1)
    - Adult literacy programs in the UK, 1975-1977; includes Adult Literacy Resource Agency, The Library Association. (Box-folder 31.2-31.4)
    - "Development of library literacy programs and services": notes, 1977, undated (Box-folder 31.5)
    - Southwestern Library Association (SwLA) Literacy Project, 1980-1981, undated; includes typewritten essay, "Libraries and Literacy: the SwLA Survey" by Carol Lynn Roddy, 1981. (Box-folder 31.6-31.7)
    - Frontier College Student Centered Individualized Learning (SCIL) program, Toronto, Canada, 1980-1983; includes The Right to Read by Marlene Webber, 1983. (Box-folder 31.8-31.9)
    - Montgomery College, Takhoma Park Campus adult literacy programs, 1982-1984;, undated includes brochures, The MAHE Journal. (Box-folder 31.10)
    - Adult book discussion clubs, 1984, 1988; includes Book Discussion Clubs for Adult New Readers by Nancy Oakley, 1988. (Box-folder 31.11)
    - WNED-TV Buffalo, NY literacy programs, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 31.12)
    - Altrusa literacy needs assessment, 1986, undated; includes notes, brochures. (Box-folder 31.13)
    - "Libraries and Literacy Education" project study, University of Wisconsin-Madison, 1986; includes correspondence. (Box-folder 32.1)
    - Center for the Book, Library of Congress, 1979-1985, 1995; includes correspondence, minutes, National Advisory Board list, 1980-1984, handbooks, brochures. (Box-folder 32.2-32.7)
    - Evaluating Library Literacy Programs, 1991, undated; includes notes, report, article. (Box-folder 32.8)
    - Other literacy programs, 1965-1966, 1990, 1995, 1998, undated (Box-folder 32.9)
  - Other literacy research, IV.D
    Lyman filed most of these folders of notes and articles by topic and the archivist kept with that organization. The subseries is in chronological order.
    - "Values," class and ethnicity, 1950-1959, 1968, undated (Box-folder 32.10)
    - Low Income Lifestyles, Lola M. Ireland, editor, 1965 (Box-folder 32.11)
    - Disadvantaged populations, 1966 (Box-folder 32.12)
    - Labor and "the aging population," 1966-1967, 1984-1985, undated (Box-folder 32.13)
    - "Communication theories," 1971, undated (Box-folder 33.1)
    - Literacy education and the role of the public library, 1974, 1986-1996, undated (Box-folder 33.2)
    - "Collection development," 1976, 1979, 1980, undated (Box-folder 33.3)
    - "Adult learning projects," 1978-1979, undated (Box-folder 33.4)
    - Workplace literacy, 1978, 1983, 1986-1990 (Box-folder 33.5-33.6)
    - Bibliographies, 1986, undated (Box-folder 33.7)
    - "Adults as learners": lecture and discussion, undated (Box-folder 33.8)
    - "Clientele," undated (Box-folder 33.9)
    - "Forces and trends: changes in society," undated (Box-folder 33.10)
    - Notes on literacy librarians in the United States, undated (Box-folder 33.11)
    - General research notes, undated; includes notes on library management, telecommunications, adult independent learning, public relations. (Box-folder 33.12-33.13)
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Contributors
American Library Association; American Library Association. Adult Services Division; Buffalo Public Library (Buffalo, N.Y.); Buffalo and Erie County Public Library (N.Y.); State University of New York at Buffalo; State University of New York at Buffalo. School of Information and Library Studies; University of Buffalo; University of Wisconsin--Madison. Library School
Subject Terms
Lyman, Helen H., 1910--Archives; Lyman, Helen H., 1910--Biography; Lyman, Helen H., 1910--Correspondence; Library science teachers--United States; College teachers--United States; Library education--United States; Adult services in public libraries--United States; Libraries and older people--United States; Libraries and illiterate persons--United States; Libraries and adult education--United States; Libraries and new literates--United States; Libraries--Cultural programs--United States; Literacy programs--United States; Libraries and community--United States; Reading (Adult education)--United States; Mentoring in library science--United States; Library science--Research; Library science literature; Library schools--New York (State)--Buffalo; Library schools--Wisconsin--Madison; Women librarians; Huguenor family; American Library Association.; American Library Association. Adult Services Division.; Buffalo and Erie County Public Library (N.Y.); Buffalo Public Library (Buffalo, N.Y.); State University of New York at Buffalo. School of Information and Library Studies; State University of New York at Buffalo. School of Information and Library Studies--Faculty; University of Buffalo--Alumni and alumnae; University of Wisconsin. Library School; University of Wisconsin. Library School--Faculty; State University of New York at Buffalo--Archives
Associated Material
Related Resources
Helen Lyman, Women's work: a tribute to the women who make UB work online exhibit http://ublib.buffalo.edu/libraries/units/archives/womens_work/ [Last accessed November 24, 2009].